Guide to the Constance Goddard DuBois papers,1897-1909.
DuBois, Constance Goddard papers,1897-1909.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Constance Goddard DuBois papers, 1897-1909.
9167
Constance Goddard. DuBois
2 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, correspondence.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The papers include her field notes from her summers in California, notes on her activities with the Connecticut Indian Association, and newspaper clippings relating to Indian affairs, particularly those in California. Drafts of manuscripts for her publications on Luiseno religion, Diegueno mythology, and other subjects relating to the Mission Indians of California are included in the collection. Letters written to Du Bois from 1897 to 1909 comprise a significant part of the collection. Correspondentss from Alfred Kroeber, Otis T. Mason, Mary C. B. Watkins, Frederick W. Hodge, and Clark Wissler, as well as with representatives of Indian-aid organizations such as the Indian Industrial League and the Indian Rights Association. Other correspondence to DuBois, her notes and manuscripts on Indians of California including the Diegueño and Luiseño Indians. One folder about Robert Wilcox and the Hawaiian Rebellion. Folders with information about mythology, religion, industry, art, missions, language, vocabulary, biographical information, and newspaper clippings. Includes index of correspondence. Field notebooks, date books, and diary books.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Constance Goddard Du Bois, a successful novelist who lived in Connecticut, became interested in the Indians of southern California on a visit there around the turn of the century. From 1897 to 1907 she became increasingly involved in efforts to assist the Luiseno and Diegueno peoples of the area, spending many of her summers with them. At home in the winter she worked vigorously to bring the situation of these desperately poor people to the attention of her neighbors and officials of the Indian Bureau, through correspondence and lectures. Her efforts put her in touch with anthropologists and other scholars with similar interests, and she began to publish some of the many myths and legends she collected from her Diegueño and Luiseño friends in southern California.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The papers include her field notes from her summers in California, notes on her activities with the Connecticut Indian Association, and newspaper clippings relating to Indian affairs, particularly those in California. Drafts of manuscripts for her publications on Luiseno religion, Diegueno mythology, and other subjects relating to the Mission Indians of California are included in the collection. Letters written to Du Bois from 1897 to 1909 comprise a significant part of the collection. Correspondentss from Alfred Kroeber, Otis T. Mason, Mary C. B. Watkins, Frederick W. Hodge, and Clark Wissler, as well as with representatives of Indian-aid organizations such as the Indian Industrial League and the Indian Rights Association. Other correspondence to DuBois, her notes and manuscripts on Indians of California including the Diegueño and Luiseño Indians. One folder about Robert Wilcox and the Hawaiian Rebellion. Folders with information about mythology, religion, industry, art, missions, language, vocabulary, biographical information, and newspaper clippings. Includes index of correspondence. Field notebooks, date books, and diary books.
SUBJECTS
Names:
DuBois, Constance Goddard.; Hodge, Frederick Webb, 1864-1956.; Kroeber, A. L.(Alfred Louis), 1876-1960.; Mason, Otis Tufton, 1838-1908.; Watkins, Mary C. B.; Wilcox, R. W.(Robert William), 1855-1903.; Wissler, Clark, 1870-1947.; Huntington Free Library.
Subjects:
Indians of North America.; Indians of Mexico.; Indian art--North America.; Indian mythology--North America.; Indians of North America--California.; Indians of North America--Education.; Indians of North America--Funeral customs and rites.; Indians of North America--History.; Indians of North America--Industries.; Indians of North America--Languages.; Indians of North America--Missions.; Indians of North America; Indians of North America--Religion.; Indians of North America--Rites and ceremonies.; Aztecs.; Diegueño Indians.; Luiseño Indians.
Places:
Hawaii--History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
The papers include her field notes from her summers in California, notes on her activities with the Connecticut Indian Association, and newspaper clippings relating to Indian affairs, particularly those in California. Drafts of manuscripts for her publications on Luiseno religion, Diegueno mythology, and other subjects relating to the Mission Indians of California are included in the collection. Letters written to Du Bois from 1897 to 1909 comprise a significant part of the collection. She corresponded with such notables in the field of anthropology as Alfred Kroeber, O.T. Mason, Frederick W. Hodge, and Clark Wissler, as well as with representatives of Indian-aid organizations such as the Indian Industrial League and the Indian Rights Association.
The Du Bois papers are a window into the lives of the Indians in southern California at the turn of the century. They are especially useful in demonstrating the relationship between the Mission Indians and those, like Constance Du Bois, who served as their intermediaries with the state and federal governments. Preserving this collection archivally on microfilm ensures its availability to future scholars, and makes it accessible in libraries throughout the country via inter-library loan. While much of the collection warrants individual preservation treatment as well, this microfilm edition is an important first step.
RELATED MATERIALS
Microfilm available.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Original Huntington Free Library box numbers have been retained.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Guides and other material
Series II. List of Correspondents
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Publications and Manuscripts
Series V. Notebooks
Series VI. Field Notebooks
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Guides and other material
  - Partial Calendar of Constance Goddard Du Bois Correspondence in the Huntington Free Library (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 1-86
  - Correspondence Chronology for Constance Goddard Du Bois, prepared by Lowell Bean (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 87-123
  - Bibliography of Published Works of Constance Goddard Du Bois, compiled by Lowell Bean (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 124
  - Transcript of Lowell Bean's Tape-Recorded Comments on the Constance Goddard Du Bois papers at the Huntington Free Library (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 125-138
  - Duplicate calendar and publications (Box 1)
- Series II. List of Correspondents
  List of correspondents in the collection, included is the microfilm reel on which the correspondent appears. Reel one includes correspondence from 1870 through 1905, reel two from 1906 through 1909.
  Acting Commissioner, Dept. of Interior to Supt., Pila School
  Reel 1
  Albanos, Jose O.
  Reel 2
  Ambler, Cleason
  Banneson (?), Thomas F.
  Barrows, David P.
  Belknap, Edwin S.
  Brosius, S.M. to J. S. Lockwood
  Campbell, Archibald
  Reel 1 and Reel 2
  Carter, Sybil
  Charles Scribner's Sons
  Collier, William
  Collins, Ella to Frances Sparhawk
  Colvick, Frederick to Otis T. Mason
  Companiero, Moaria la
  Cornelius, Laura M.
  County Magazine editors
  Daniels, John
  Daniels, John to Frederick J. Kingsbury
  Davenport, John Gaylord
  Davis, E.H.
  Davis, J.E.
  Dixon, Roland B.
  Dixon, Zella Allen
  Dorsey, George A.
  Doubleday, ??
  Doubleday Page & Co.
  Du Bois to C.F. Larrabee
  Du Bois to Commissioner, General Land Office
  Du Bois to F.E. Leupp
  Du Bois to F.W. Hodge
  Du Bois to her mother
  Du Bois to Santo Lopez
  Duffield & Co. Publishers
  Engler, Anna G.
  Field, E.G.
  Gagnon, Alph.
  Games, Thomas M.
  Goizley (?), M.
  Hall, J. Thomas
  Henderson, Victor
  Hicks, Gilbert H.
  Hitchcock, Geo. N.
  Hitchcock, George N. to Jose Santo Lopez
  Hodge, F.W.
  Hough, Walter
  Jessop, Joseph
  Johnson, Joseph H.
  Jones, W. (?)
  Kelsey, C.E.
  Kingsbury, Frederick
  Kroeber, A.L.
  Larrabee, C.F.
  Larrabee, C.F. to Charles E. Shell
  Larrabee, C.F. to Frederick J. Kingsbury
  Leupp, Francis E.
  Lockwood, J.S.
  Lopez, Jose Santo
  Lummis, Charles F.
  MacCurdy, George Grant
  Mason, O.T.
  Merriam, C. Hart
  Merrill, Elmer D.
  Monsen, Frederick I.
  Mooch, C.A.
  Neiler, Sophie R.
  Nejo (?), Rosalie
  Partridge, Charles L.
  Peabody, Margaret A.
  Peak, George
  Perham, Mrs. F.E.
  Redmond, Lucy R.
  Restarick, H.B.
  Robinson, Mamie
  Rondfit, S.V.
  Rotassza (?), S.
  Rugg, Harold Goddard
  Russ, N.M.
  Russell, Francis S.
  Scribner, G. Hilton
  Shell, Charles E.
  Smith, Wayland H.
  Sniffen, M.K.
  Sparhawk, Francis C.
  Sophie?
  Stevenson, Matilda Coxe
  Vinia, Alice to Miss Andrews
  Warren, Mary B.
  Watkins, Mary B.
  Watkins, Mary to Mrs. A.G. Dubois
  Watkins, Mary to Rev. H.B. Restarick
  Welsh, Herbert
  Wissler, Clark
  Wood, Donzetta
  Women's Medical Center, NY
  Yedelsbah, Y(?)innah
- Series III. Correspondence
  - Childhood Correspondence of Constance Goddard Du Bois, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 183
  - Correspondence, August 1897 - December 1900 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 199
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 372
  - Correspondence, January 1902 - December 1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 467
  - Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 613
  - Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Also available on Reel 1, Frame 743
  - Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 1
  - Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 171
  - Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 371
  - Correspondence, January - June 1909 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 491
  - Sparkman Murder Correspondence and Clippings, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 551
- Series IV. Publications and Manuscripts
  - Offprints of Publications by Constance Goddard Du Bois (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 574
  - Publication: The Song of Death (Box 1, Folder 16A)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 612
  - Incomplete manuscript, The Religion of the Luiseno and Diegueno Indians of Southern California. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 621
  - Songs. Incomplete Stories. [oversize] (Box 2, Folder 17A)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 674
  - The Chungichnish Worship (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 683
  - Ceremonies and Traditions of the Diegueno Indians (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 846
  - Chaup Songs (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 865
  - A Desert Flower (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 875
  - Notebook containing Hatakeki Story of Cuy-oh-lo-mau (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Description of things for Museum; Version of Chaup Story; Connection with Mojaves
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 898
  - Indian Summer in South California, A Brush Church, Ella (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Also available on Reel 2, Frame 955
  - Indian Summer in Southern California (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 1
  - Mission Indian Folklore: The Culture Hero (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Chaup
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 9
  - Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Partially illustrated with photographs (some missing); Incomplete
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 43
  - Mission Indian Myth and Song (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Two Versions
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 83
  - Eagle Story (Box 1, Folder 27A)
    Four Versions
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 112
  - Myths and Folklore of Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 125
  - The Story of the Mesa Grande Indians [oversized] (Box 2, Folder 28A)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 166
  - The mythology of the Dieguenos, Mission Indians of San Diego County, California (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 179
  - Cinon's Story [oversized] (Box 2, Folder 29A)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 199
  - Mythology of the Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 206
  - The Mythology of the Diegueno and it's Relation to that of the Aztecs (Box 1, Folder 30A)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 227
  - A Preliminary Account of the Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Published in JAFL as Mythology of the Mission Indians
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 242
  - Primitive Woman and Her Modern Sister (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 249
  - Questions for Guidance in the Field (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 258
  - The Religion and Myths of the Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 282
  - Religious Ceremonials and Myths of the Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 295
  - Mythology of the Mission Indians, Part 2 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    The Sandpainting Among the Luiseno; Myths and Myth Songs
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 400
  - The Return to the Primitive (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 414
  - The Symbolism of Indian Basketry (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 421
  - Art and Industry among the Mission Indians (Box 1, Folder 38A)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 437
  - Studies of the Mission Indians: Myths and Customs of the Dieguenos of San Diego County, California (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 449
  - History of Ollas (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Notes on Campo(?); Genealogy Information
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 458
  - To the Members and Friends of the Waterbury Indian Association (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 465
  - Notes on Hawaii (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 470
  - Miscellany I. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 523
  - Miscellaneous Notes including Notes on Compulsory Education [oversize] (Box 2, Folder 43B)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 691
  - Miscellany II. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Includes genealogical information on family of Robert Singleton Peabody
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 710
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 745
  - Newspaper Clippings - Perry's Second Artic Expedition (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 864
  - Newspaper Clippings [oversize] (Box 2, Folder 46A)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 874
  - Newspaper Clippings [oversize] (Box 2, Folder 46B)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 915
  - Clippings and Indian Association Members [oversize] (Box 2, Folder 46C)
    Also available on Reel 3, Frame 929
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 1
  - Music - Chaup Songs (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 19
  - Undated Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 26
  - Biographical Information on Du Bois and Monro (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 65
- Notebooks
  - Date Book for 1906 (Box 2, Volume 51)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 75
  - Memorandum - Letter and brochure from F.A. Bancel enclosed. Notes, addresses, miscellany (Box 2, Volume 52)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 233
  - Stars of Springs/Songs (Box 2, Volume 53)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 293
  - Arts and Industries of the Mission Indians (Box 2, Volume 54)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 367
  - Cook Book Recipes, Music, and Notes (Box 2, Volume 55)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 390
  - Sandpainting Among the Luisenos, etc. (Box 2, Volume 56)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 429
  - Indian Workers and Record (Box 2, Volume 57)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 475
- Field Notebooks
  Selected "Cover" Titles Given
  - Salvador's Story, Sandpainting (Box 2, Volume 58)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 524
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 2, Volume 59)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 630
  - Cinon's Story (Box 2, Volume 60)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 749
  - Notes from Ethnographic Reports, Cinon, Chaup Story, Eagle Story, etc. (Box 2, Volume 61)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 781
  - A Generous Bore, Notes from Ethnographies, Tarahumara (Box 2, Volume 62)
    Also available on Reel 4, Frame 949
  - Notes taken at Mesa Grande (Box 2, Volume 63)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 1
  - Lucarno's Story and Song,and Albanez's Songs (Box 2, Volume 64)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 146
  - LaJolla I. (Box 2, Volume 65)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 269
  - Reservations and Villages, Folk-lore, Lummis House (Box 2, Volume 66)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 401
  - Notes on Elizabeth and Robert Browning, The Entrance Upon Literature of the North American Indian (Box 2, Volume 67)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 475
  - LaJolla and Mesa Grande, Notes from Dellenbaugh and Miss Fletcher, Music (Box 2, Volume 68)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 631
  - Songs of Creation, Jose, 1903 (Box 2, Volume 69)
  - Indian Members, The Soft-Hearted Sioux (Box 2, Volume 70)
    by Zitkala-Sa and Notes on other Indian Authors
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 726
  - Folk-lore I, Diary of Trip, Language, Jose's Story, etc. (Box 2, Volume 71)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 785
  - Indian Summer I, Persian Alphabet, Zoroastrianism, etc. (Box 2, Volume 72)
    Also available on Reel 5, Frame 900
  - The Religions of the North American Indian, Faith's Warrant in Science, Letter to Editor, etc., Cushing's Cock Story (Box 2, Volume 73)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1
  - Manzanita Basketry: A Revival, Indian Prisoners, Fiestas, etc., Chaup Songs, Mr. Collier's Paper (Box 2, Volume 74)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 115
  - Campo 1 - Sant's Addition to Chaup Story and Songs (Box 2, Volume 75)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 208
  - Indian as Agriculturalist (Box 2, Volume 76)
    Captions for photos (photos gone), Tickets for Steroptican lecture, etc.
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 294
  - Account of Mission Indians, Star Myths of the Mission Indians, Image Fiesta (Box 2, Volume 77)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 358
  - The Primitive Indian as Agriculturalist, Halley's Comet (Box 2, Volume 78)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 420
  - Notes and Myths, Names of Months (Box 2, Volume 79)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 492
  - Sandpainting and Songs (Box 2, Volume 80)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 593
  - Campo-Manzanita, Stars and Star Myths, Religious Myth of the Mission Indians (Box 2, Volume 81)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 637
  - Studies of the Mission Indians: The Diegueno, The Women of Forty (Box 2, Volume 82)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 726
  - LaJolla II - Notes, Language (Box 2, Volume 83)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 860
  - California Indians (Box 2, Volume 84)
    Extracts from Venegas and Jacob Baegert
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 895
  - Notes from Brinton's Myths and Others (Box 2, Volume 85)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1053
  - Notes for Book re: Bancroft, etc., and Primitive Art for Modern Buyers (Box 2, Volume 86)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1153
  - Campo Note Book II (Box 2, Volume 87)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1177
  - Campo Notes rewritten, Potrero Notes, Lucario's Story, con't. (Box 2, Volume 88)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1245
  - Extracts: Wagner's letter to Matiloe Wesendonck; from Wm. von Humboldt; Charlotte von Stein (?) / Boyesen's Estimate of Goethe; Diegueno Myths and their Connection with the Mohave (Box 2, Volume 89)
    Also available on Reel 6, Frame 1280